[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is a sutta in the Anguttara Nikaya Book of Sevens, 7.49.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in regard to seven perceptions that are encouraged to be developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: The first one is the perception of a subha, or the non-beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's call it the ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the perception of the ugly is developed and frequently practiced, it is of great fruit and great benefit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when a bhikkhu often lives with such a purpose, his mind shrinks back and goes in the opposite direction and turns away from engaging in sexual intercourse.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, either equanimity
[SPEAKER_00]: All the opposite direction of what the mind is attending to, gets established, if he practices this asubha.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, either his mind turns away from sexual intercourse, or he gets based in equanimity, or his mind gets established in that opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Of what he's attending to, which is the beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: And that Pāḷi term is patikula manasikāra, usually translated as repulsive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, his mind gets established in the repulsive.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's, it's the other...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the other side.
[SPEAKER_00]: The other side of what he's attending to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the other side of what is being attended.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pāṭi, against.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's against the directly opposite, as in the opposite side of the beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the side that's simultaneously there, not the opposite side in response to beauty.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the point, the opposite side.
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you know?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in order to define an opposite, you need to have that thing that this opposes it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the whole point of the opposite side is to recognize that the ugly
[SPEAKER_01]: is present opposite to the beautiful, while beautiful is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not something you need to find, like, in response to beautiful, but it's more like something you need to discern within the beautiful as the opposite side.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, if you say the two sides of the coin, you don't seek the second coin to see the other side of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same coin, but now you need to see the opposite side, the one you're not looking at.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason why that's so important is because most people, most commonly, the way people practice the asubha is in response to the beautiful, as in you want to get rid of the beautiful and replace it with the ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, those are just two separate things for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not seeing that ugly within that beautiful, which is how you would cancel the beautiful, by seeing the opposite of it within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But instead, you're just trying to get rid of the beautiful, because it bothers you, and replace it with ugly, because that supposedly not bothers you, or it shouldn't bother you as much, if you want to practice the restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in reality, what you're doing is just acting on account of how you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the beautiful is there, bothering you, and you just want to be free from bother, which is fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to be free from bother, but how you go about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you go about blaming the beautiful for the bother?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, implicitly, yes, because you're trying to get rid of the beautiful by replacing it with the ugly, which you're supposed to be cultivating.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that means you're just... you don't really know where the bother is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the bother is not in the beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: The lust is not in the beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: None of that is in the beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in your own...
[SPEAKER_01]: Lack of understanding of it, not seeing the nature of it, attraction to it, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because you don't see the nature of that beautiful thing, that's why you're attracted to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and you will not see the nature, because now you think, oh, the attraction, the whole thing is in the beautiful, so all I need to do is replace the beautiful with these images of ugly, and then I'm free from attraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what happened to many monks who were practicing wrongly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then they started getting attracted to the ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, while beautiful is present, you have a chance
[SPEAKER_01]: To discern correctly, that like yoniso, manasikāra, to attend correctly, to attend to the opposite side of it, that is there, implicit, which is why freedom from the side that is beautiful, is possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't have to do anything in response to it, you just need to see through it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, if you actually develop that, doesn't matter what type of beautiful perception you encounter later on in the future, the mind remains equally developed in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind sees through it, because it has seen through its nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that beautiful is based on that which is not beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's inseparable from.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you will not necessarily see there's based upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you start with the beautiful being put first, the nature of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: It shouldn't be first, but being put first, there's no first point.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no... it's beginningless, the attitude that putting the beautiful first, assuming the beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: It shouldn't be there, because if you look through it, you just see the ugly, but it is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you start as a person with a mind that's not free from ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why if you uproot it, you cannot go back to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, actually, if you see through the nature of beautiful, as inseparable from ugly, then you realize this is not beautiful, it's just less ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not as ugly, but equally ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means equally start serving as a basis for dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that brings me to, I want to say, when you read that first, the opening, like, oh, he cultivates perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: How, like, how do you cultivate the perception?
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Attending to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Attending to certain perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can either attend to the beautiful or you can...
[SPEAKER_01]: What else?
[SPEAKER_00]: By knowing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to... say, you want to establish your mind in the perception of ugly, now.
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you... how would you do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you discern the opposite side?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, look at the the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: See the bigger picture.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Of that beautiful... whatever I'm finding beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need the beautiful first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you... and that's... that's when the... when we would say you should, like, keep
[SPEAKER_01]: Rechecking, so to speak, your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there lost in it now?
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, is there presently enduring attraction to beautiful right here, right now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then the answer is no.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then it's like, oh, but could there be lost in this mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, in the future, in the moments to come, is my mind liable?
[SPEAKER_01]: To become attracted again to something of sensual nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just about, oh, now I have to go and look, or taste, or touch, or engage in any form with sensual objects in order to see the ugly through it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not engaging through sensual objects, practicing sense exchange, you get to see the liability towards the attraction, which is present attraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you are not... you will not be liable to be attracted to things in the future, if that liability is not presently enduring as a form of attraction already.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's when people sometimes judge how you... you need to... almost like how you need to flirt with your kilesas, to see... to learn about them.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're actually flirting with... giving in to the weakness.
[SPEAKER_01]: By giving in to the weakness, you're not going to see your liability, because you're already acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to not engage with sensuality, and then see that another reflection that will say, so, is my mind liable to future arising of these things?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can lust, greed, aversion, delusion, arise in this mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not here now, but could they be here?
[SPEAKER_01]: And he says, yes, they can be here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, why will this thing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, because I haven't abandoned things right here, right now, on account of which lust arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Depending which angle you want to take on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, you want to recognize that the possibility of last aversion delusion manifesting in your experience is already last aversion delusion in your experience, just on a subtler level.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to wait for the central last aversion delusion to say, okay, now I have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to restrain from it and then recognize the possibility of those things arising in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, how would you know this possibility of lust arising in the future, unless that possibility of lust is already present, right here, right now, which is how you know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you can discern that possibility...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's... that's already... that's basically the roots of lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, the possibility of lust, as the Buddha said, is because... is there, because basis for lust is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't abandoned it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, circumstantially, you're not particularly, specifically experiencing any lust right here, right now, but the whole basis, the whole domain of being liable to lust is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why, if you look at it, can these things arise in the future?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, means, oh, I'm presently still maintaining their basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the conditions are right, lust will arise on account of the basis that I'm maintaining.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what you recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what would be the basis for lust arising?
[SPEAKER_00]: The future lust arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: Valuing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Valuing of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is no pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not engaging in an essential pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you're maintaining the view that that pleasure is valuable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or not even that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's enough to maintain the view that that pleasure is not dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's enough to maintain the basis for future lust to arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not seeing danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly if you see the extent of the danger, as the Buddha would say, you free yourself from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is the extent of gratification.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as I haven't understood the danger, the extent of the danger in regard to that gratification, I did not claim I am fully free from sensual desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when I understood the danger, then you understood the escape, then he claimed that he's fully free from sensual desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, within the beautiful, the opposite side of the beautiful is the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's defined by that beautiful, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a separate thing you have to take on as a separate contemplation, as a result of witnessing the beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: There is the beautiful, perception of beautiful, perception of attraction, perception of lust, enduring in this mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that, I need to discern that thing as dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could already see, like, cultivation of perception is not done on the particular level of this perception, that perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's done on the level of the domain of perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you are perceiving the fact that you are liable to future lust, to future centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is a perception in your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That liability is seen, is perceived.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not in regard to anything particular experienced by eyes, nose, mouth, ears, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the cultivation of perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why he called, like, in other sutras, perception of light, perception of boundlessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: None of these things are specific.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, can you see boundlessness with your eyes?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, these perceptions are mental in regard to the sense domain, in regard to the eyes and so on, in regard to sense organs.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not about looking at this, not looking at that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about seeing the liability to pleasure, to lust, to craving on the level of your mind, perceiving there and seeing... perceiving the danger in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another perception you develop.
[SPEAKER_01]: The danger within this perception is also perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you cultivate it long enough, next time your eye sees beautiful, the danger is seen through that beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: With your eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you develop it sufficiently with your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: The significance of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before it's even... before the particular beautiful thing has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before... that has been developed before.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what I'm saying is, if you're free from sensuality,
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when a particular essential thing has arisen and seen, it's the danger is seen, not the beautiful of it, which requires ignoring the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: You, through development of that right perception of danger, the opposite side implicit in it, seeing it, learning how to basically maintain it in its enduring,
[SPEAKER_01]: That will culminate to the point of where you will stop putting that beautiful first.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will stop being the reference point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, it's the danger and the ugliness is the reference point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then the difference is only like how ugly and how dangerous it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like it's not dangerous, it's beautiful and then sometimes gets... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always ugly, it's always dangerous, just sometimes it's more dangerous, sometimes it's less dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, you don't go near it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes I'm near the poison, sometimes poison is far away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, I'm not engaging with it, because it's poison.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, so it says here that opposite side gets established once you have developed that perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are the things that your mind will turn away from.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Prospects of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be dispassionate, equanimous towards...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the development of perception, then, means development of the right characteristics.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're implicit in it, but you choose to ignore them.
[SPEAKER_01]: The main chief of those characteristics being the danger, the peril, the risk.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that sign of the danger gets established.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind is composed within that knowledge that now you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't forget about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, because everything is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't need to keep thinking danger, danger, danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to keep seeing, hearing, smelling, tasting, touching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Danger becomes implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, a possibility of pleasure is implicit for the mind not free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, mind free from sensuality has replaced the possibility for pleasure with possibility of pain and danger and something you will shy away from.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to maintain your freedom from centrality and protect it, because that's not freedom, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Freedom means you're free.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're literally freed, because you replaced it correctly, you reversed the order, and you fixed it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: You healed it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's learning how to... And that's, again, the subtle thing I'm trying to point out here, is that, inevitably, you have to start with, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Fabricating the perception of danger upon centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's dangerous, is dangerous, is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: And usually in response to centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, there's... the mind has perceived centrality, craves, it wants it, it wants the pleasure, it's so painful, I must get rid of it, I must get rid of it, I must get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as you have that attitude, you will not be able to see through that which you're trying to get rid of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't want to get rid of the... the sensuality as the cause for your bother.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to get rid of your attraction towards sensuality that's kind of indifferent to your bother.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said, for to target the beautiful things remaining in the world, he still perceived this is beautiful, this is ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is what used to excite me, now it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't lose perception of what's agreeable, what's disagreeable, but you lose attraction to it, because you've seen the danger through in that attraction to beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for as long as you're trying to replace and get rid of the beautiful, you're not seeing the opposite side of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, literally,
[SPEAKER_01]: The coin given to you, you're so scared of its face, because you might have a desire for it, so you try to get rid of, replace the coin, but how can you then see what's behind it?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the other side of that coin?
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to allow it to endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why sense restraint is absolutely not negotiable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because sense restraint is that prerequisite, that sort of precondition of you developing sufficient strength to be able to allow the beautiful thing, if it has a reason, you don't seek it out,
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it has... and it will arise, because you're not free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: When it arises, you don't want to get rid of it, you want to see through it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for that, it needs to endure with that like a sharp inciting sort of edge.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you have developed your behavior beforehand, as the Buddha would say, you will not act out of it, which means you get to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you get to see then your responsibility for your own attraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not in things, it's in your own unchecked craving towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you get to see the asubha of subha, true subha.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will not see that on the level of the eye, nose, smell, ears, sound and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those will remain agreeable or disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when those are agreeable, within that, you want to know the danger of it, because it is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you transcend both sense organs and sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being developed in regard to your own body.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in seeing it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing the danger for it, not cultivating lust and passion and desire towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, the simile, like, like a beautiful young woman or a young man in their youth and somebody puts a dead snake around their neck.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wouldn't they be, like, disgusted, appalled, just get rid of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you should cultivate attitude towards your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, oh, within this body, that's healthy, that's okay, that I don't see any problem with it at the moment, you need to, like, oh, I'm a... you can't get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you need to do within that, because you only have one body, so you can't just replace it with a more suitable body for contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you certainly don't want to wait until you get sick, old and falling apart.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you then practice this repulsiveness attitude of non-lust and danger within that which you can't see that it's repulsive?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will never see it as repulsive, because it's you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you cultivate it on the level of that liability that we spoke about.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, this factually, currently healthy, relatively young, strong and so on body,
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that, I mustn't try to get rid of that, because I can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, within that, I need to see the danger of that beautiful, agreeable, healthy life, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't deny that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will fall into the denial if you try to ugly, ugly, and visualize, and just visualize this disgust, disgust.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, that's a separate thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're not seeing it on the relevant basis of beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not seeing it through the beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just doing it in response to it, which means you're denying the first thing of beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the next... by denying the first things of beautiful that you perceive, you're denying the basis of beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, I'm seeing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you're maintaining the basis of beautiful for the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your practice of asubha will be valid for as long as your determination lasts.
[SPEAKER_01]: To look at ugly, look at ugly, look at ugly, look at ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no wisdom coming out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because wisdom remains even when you stop making the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you stop making the effort, it lasts back.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, your mind...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, which means what the Buddha said, which means that, on account of which, the future lustful manifest hasn't been abandoned in me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you abandon it by seeing the danger within the beautiful, not by trying to replace the beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't... you didn't create it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The arising had nothing to do with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will inevitably have to act out of the attitude of denying it, by blaming it for your own attraction, and trying to get rid of it, and replace it with perceptions of a subha, because that's more wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to be restrained by body, by speech, by mind, but then you need to allow it to endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the unpleasant bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having sensuality endure, you know, and not act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the satipaṭṭhāna, if it's done rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows the mind of sensuality, mind affected with sensuality, as mind affected with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not he knows mind of sensuality and then he gets rid of that sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is in sensual domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not his doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But his doing is, if he does what?
[SPEAKER_01]: If he welcomes that domain, if he entertains it, if he delights in it, if he acts out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I will not get rid of the domain of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I will get rid of my delight, my attitude towards it, which is why the domain of sensuality keeps coming back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I keep welcoming it in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same like when the Buddha said, actually,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, the Mara said to his daughters, who tried to see, like, sort of, entice the mind of the Buddha, he said, oh, you're wasting your time.
[SPEAKER_01]: I spent seven years of getting back to him and trying to get him out and he's nowhere to be seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you stop engaging with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mara still might be jumping around, you're trying to entertain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's until, basically, he sees that you're irreversible.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible for you to step back into that domain and then these things will even stop from appearing to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, like flies landing when there is still, like, bad smell or open wounds.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you might have healed, but the fly is still trying to find a place where they can land.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, the simile the Buddha used is like a crow trying to find a... No, sorry, the simile the Mahārāja used was like a crow trying to find an edible bit that he can bite on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he kept coming back to it, kept searching, kept digging, and in the end, he gives up.
[SPEAKER_01]: After six, seven years, the Mahārāja gave up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, seven years is still... Yeah, but none of those seven years were bothered for the Buddha, because the bother is never in the Mara or Mara's things.
[SPEAKER_01]: The bother is in you, like, inadvertently, through your own choice, lacking awareness, lacking the danger, perception of danger, wandering straight into Mara's domain, on and on and on, and then keeping yourself there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the bother.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is just nuisance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like heat, wind, rain... perceptions of beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, learning how to allow beautiful to endure without acting out of it,
[SPEAKER_01]: It can then reveal the other side.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or then, rather, if you learn how to allow beautiful to endure when it has arisen, not act out of it, know the mind affected with sensuality as mind affected with sensuality, then thoughts of a subha will actually start to apply correctly, as the counterpart of this very same thing here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Counterpart that doesn't deny the beautiful, just reveals its other side.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, continuing in regards to those perceptions that need to be developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: When a bhikkhu becomes accustomed to the perception of death, their mind draws back from attachment to life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And either equanimity gets established or that other side gets established.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, either he becomes quite dispassionate or, again,
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly the same what we discussed in the previous section.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, you can afford to practice a subha at the expense of denying subha, but, see, you can't practice mindfulness of death at the expense of denying life, because you have to be alive in order to practice mindfulness of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the perception of that death is counterpart of this life here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can just get rid of it in order to see what death is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is how people practice asubha, usually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Get rid of the sensuality and then just hammer in asubha, asubha, asubha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, look at something happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: Look at something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now, you must... to practice the perception of death, you must die.
[SPEAKER_00]: You must not be alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You must die and then look at it, stare at it for long enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the other... that's why many people say, oh, the other side.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means the other side is there, simultaneously present, at the same time, within this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Within whatever you're attending.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the death is simultaneously present as the other side of life.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you are alive right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't attend it, necessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not attending the fact that you're alive, you're just taking it for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: In its nature, death is implicit.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it wouldn't be implicit if there is no life.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, a subha would not be implicit if there is no subha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you actually, instead of following the direction that taking your life for granted offers, you start discerning, whenever there is life, death is implicit, and start developing that subtle, implicit, opposite perception of death within the life, you will experience disenchantment towards life.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be impossible for you to remain attracted to life.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to be able to see that life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to be able to see for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you have to be able to see subha for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't practice asubha until you've actually understood what subha is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you will not understand what subha is, because you just keep trying to get rid of it, because it's too painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that subha, sorry, is that attraction, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's so beautiful, but it's that... For you, there is no attraction without subha, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can even be attracted to genuine as subha, because you're seeing it as subha, because of your attraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you're free from attraction, subha will still remain, but you wouldn't be attracted to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to be able to see the phenomenon of life, to discern the implicit danger of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: To see the other side of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The dangerous...
[SPEAKER_01]: The other side of the coin.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not a different coin.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not a second coin.
[SPEAKER_01]: The same coin.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, yeah, you get to see the dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it weren't dangerous, the Buddha wouldn't have said you should abandon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not seeing the danger, it's because you are not seeing the danger, not because it's not dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's something you need to take on faith in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha says that it is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have nothing to lose if you start practicing towards seeing the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only gain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, whatever... you see it, life, correctly...
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever's happening in life, you're not... you won't be taken... you're impassioned by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because the passion is... passion is not the product of life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Passion is product of you thinking or having a view that that life is yours, that that life is in your control, that that life is not subject to change, that that life will not end, that that life will last forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: All these are implicit, basically, notions that you have towards life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Enhanced passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, passion is because of your notions, misconceptions about life.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you have passion towards life.
[SPEAKER_01]: You remove the misconceptions of life, no base for passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, as I said, you cannot remove the misconceptions of life by denying life.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot remove misconceptions about beautiful by trying to constantly get rid of it and denying it, because it bothers you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You remove misconceivings by allowing beautiful to endure and then working on your misconceivings of it, in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... we said it many times.
[SPEAKER_01]: We said, like, if the central thought manifests, he... and that's what people misunderstand.
[SPEAKER_01]: He does... he does away... he gets rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, oh, but how does he go about getting rid of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Does Buddha say he denies it?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: He gets rid of it by not welcoming it, by not delighting in it, by not entertaining it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, that's how you get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Indirectly, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't get rid of it, but I will not think this, I will not think this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not think this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why you're thinking it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why that kind of denial always results in build-up of frustrations, because you're contradicting yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not think sensual thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which thoughts?
[SPEAKER_01]: The sensual thoughts that you're thinking, because you don't want to think them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, you get rid of it, but how?
[SPEAKER_01]: You get rid of the sensual thoughts, or you get rid of the intoxication with life, but not carelessly welcoming it, delighting in it, entertaining it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, so it arises on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not welcome it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't mean I'll go out and chase it away, or try to kill it, or get... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will just make sure I remain mindful of not welcoming it with any gesture, or any implication, or any hint.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not give in to welcoming this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you do that long enough, the thing will go away.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you got rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, you don't have to go and seek out, you know, death or possibility of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because it's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you seek out, means you still imply, with your view, that the problem is in those individual things that you are now seeking out to prove to yourself that you are not subjected to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you obviously are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're always close to death.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's straying from those things you ask yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I subject to this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means it's already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is there to seek out when it's already there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can future lust manifest in me, in the future?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I'm not sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless you know that it can't, that's the basis for yes, it can.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's already there, right there, experienced right there and then, here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is there to seek?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you seek out the individual,
[SPEAKER_01]: Examples of lust, or so on, to prove to yourself that you're not lustful, means you're fully lustful, and you still think the problem is in those individual things that you perceive, not in your mind of welcoming, delighting, entertaining it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can ask yourself, am I subject to death?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Will I be affected if my life were to end next second?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you then free yourself from death without denying life?
[SPEAKER_01]: By seeing the danger in life and removing slightest passion towards life, while the life is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you know, ah, it's the passion that kept me bound to life that's subject to death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not life in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, freedom from life is possible, without needing to die.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, when you do die, as the Buddha would say, you will not be reappearing anywhere else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you have severed any bond with the entire domain of society.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any inclination towards...
[SPEAKER_01]: Death is where life is, of any kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you remove slightest passion towards that life, there is no basis for death to apply to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's another perception, the perception of the other side of eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you develop that perception,
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind draws back from the craving for tastes and or you just get equanimous.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Developing the other side of eating or the other side of food, consuming food.
[SPEAKER_00]: What else is there while you're eating, experiencing all these tastes and so on?
[SPEAKER_00]: What are all the reasons that you're eating in the first place?
[SPEAKER_00]: All the digestion, going down, chewing, digesting... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, all of that is... is sort of... is secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: To the point that you prioritize the pleasure of eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what you put first.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, when you're starving, really, really hungry, losing the sight of that as the reason for your eating,
[SPEAKER_00]: You will be automatically eating out of pleasure for the taste, not of the need for food.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the other side of the eating is, doesn't matter how much you enjoy it or not enjoy it, is something you have to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a need.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a necessity.
[SPEAKER_01]: But forgetting that it's a necessity, or rather,
[SPEAKER_01]: Taking for granted that necessity, covering it up as a necessity, you then get picky.
[SPEAKER_01]: You then start speaking tastes and start acting out of taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: But doesn't matter how much acting out of taste you go for, it's still within the necessity.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still need to eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the horrible thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the horrible thing, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I need to eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the fact that I have to eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, your hunger is affecting you, your body, physically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if I don't, I'm... that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, destroying you, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the pressure of eating is there, but you ignore that, because you took food for granted, and then, on account of it, you develop now priority of tastes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Priority of pleasure, which is fully within that need.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you need to do is uncover the need that you covered up as the first.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, taste is the second, not the other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: But by covering up that need, the pressure, the hunger, the unpleasantness of it, the being subjected to it, covering that up, you put joy for the taste first, you put pleasure first.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a slave taking delight in the master, somehow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: A slave forgetting is a slave.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Forgetting is a slave.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then taking delight in the fact that he's being beaten every day.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's lovely.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has to do all this work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, more like finding a preference in how he's going to be beaten that day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Finding joy in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Forgetting that he has no choice about being beaten.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being subjected to discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, you're subjected to discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you go through beating, beating stops for a bit, then it comes back.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, instead of seeing, is there a way out of this entire situation of being subjected to beating in the first place, he just focuses on what would be the agreeable ways of receiving my beating.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's that craving for taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of investing his effort in finding the way out of his slavery altogether, where he won't be receiving any beatings, any punishment, his efforts are invested in pursuing, you know, maybe a silky whip or something else that's not as as coarse as other forms of beating.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's still something you have to go through.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, oh, so through your own chasing of
[SPEAKER_01]: Refined forms of punishment, you keep yourself still bound to the punishment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that food... developing that... necessity of food...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't ignore the fact that food is a necessity, that you are subjected to it unpleasantly,
[SPEAKER_01]: You will then not lose the context of why you eat, why you need to eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't matter how agreeable or disagreeable the punishment is, how much enjoyable this is, it's still within the unpleasant, not enjoying fact of hunger.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the hunger disappears, you stop eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you see the disease of that hunger.
[SPEAKER_00]: The greatest disease is hunger, wasn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is affliction.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're constantly afflicted by hunger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the greatest affliction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're just... your way of dealing with affliction is not freeing yourself from being liable to affliction altogether.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your way is just finding the pleasurable aspects of affliction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still affliction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not really dealing with anything, just covering it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that enjoyment of taste and cooking and recipes and so on... Yeah, that comes out of putting that first, putting that, that...
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you see that other side, that necessity of food, it becomes quite ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_00]: The passion for this taste will disappear, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems like quite a bit...
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be like, like... Well, it would be impossible to make the effort towards it, towards the taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't mean that, like, you will not taste it, if something is agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, it would be impossible for any amount of agreeable or disagreeable taste to disturb your mind, or to, like, tip back that picture into putting first, which is second, and putting second, which is first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Taste is always second.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasure to taste or displeasure of taste is always second.
[SPEAKER_01]: To hunger.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for you, taste is the first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving is the first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else is second.
[SPEAKER_01]: You even forget about hunger.
[SPEAKER_01]: You even forget to cheat out of hunger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why then people eat even when they're not hungry.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just seeking out the taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the taste is now the criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pleasure of the taste is a criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't matter how great, how refined that criteria you might have developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still within the need of hunger.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there's no need for food, you wouldn't be engaging with food.